<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--  
/*********************************************************************/
/* Copyright 2017 IBM Corp.                                          */
/*                                                                   */
/* Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");   */
/* you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.  */
/* You may obtain a copy of the License at                           */
/*                                                                   */
/* http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0                        */
/*                                                                   */
/* Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software*/
/* distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, */
/* WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. */
/* See the License for the specific language governing permissions and */
/* limitations under the License.                                   */
/*********************************************************************/     
-->
<workflowInfo>
	<workflowID>Transparent Cloud Tiering
	</workflowID><workflowDescription>Workflow for Setting up of Transparent Cloud Tiering on DFSMS</workflowDescription>
	<workflowVersion>1.0</workflowVersion>
	<vendor>IBM</vendor>
	<Configuration>
		<productID>ABC123</productID>
		<productName>Product ABC</productName>
		<productVersion>Version 1</productVersion>
 	</Configuration>
</workflowInfo>

<step name="ds8000"><title>Set up a cloud on your DS8000</title><description>Setting up a cloud on DS8000 storage hardware </description><instructions>Perform the cloud set up steps as documented in your DS8000 information. 
For information about setting up your DS8000, see <a href="http://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/ST8NCA/product_welcome/ds8000_kcwelcome.html">www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/ST8NCA/product_welcome/ds8000_kcwelcome.html.
</a><p>Note: Initially, the DS8000 only supports a single account. With only a single account, there is no way to separate test data from production data. 
Additionally, there is no way to separate HSM data from DSS data. It is recommended that using both DFSMShsm and DFSMSdss for the same account should only be done in a test environment. 
DFSMSdss and DFSMShsm should not share a single account in a production environment.</p></instructions><weight>1</weight></step><step name="tcpip"><title>Ensure TCP/IP is enabled</title><description>Ensuring TCP/IP is enabled on z/OS </description><instructions>Ensure that TCP/IP is enabled on your z/OS host system.</instructions><weight>1</weight></step><step name="provider"><title>Obtain cloud provider information</title><description>Obtain the following information from your cloud provider or administrator.</description><instructions>Obtain the following information from your cloud provider or administrator:<ul>
<li>Provider:<ul><li>SWIFT (if your cloud is an Openstack-based Swift object storage cloud using the built-in Tempauth authorization system).
</li>
<li>SWIFT-KEYSTONE (if your cloud is an Openstack-based Swift object storage cloud using the Keystone Identity service).</li>
</ul>
<li>Identity: <ul><li>a concatenation of the tenant name and a user name for that tenant in the form <i>tenant_name:user_name</i>.<p>In order to secure the cloud password, DFSMShsm data must have its own account and should not be intermixed with other data. </p></li></ul></li>
<li>Endpoint: <ul><li>the Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) that DFSMS should use when authenticating with your object storage cloud.<p>Note: when SWIFT-KEYSTONE is the provider, the endpoint must contain the version number of the identity API to use. Currently, only the version 2 API is supported. For example,
if the endpoint is <i>https://dallas.ibm.com</i>, the endpoint in the SMS construct should be <i>https://dallas.ibm.com/v2.0</i> . </p></li></ul></li>
<li>Port Number: <ul><li>the port on which DFSMS is to communicate with the endpoint.</li></ul></li>
<li>SSL Version: <ul><li>the lowest acceptable level of SSL/TLS that should be used when establishing a secure connection.</li></ul></li>
</li></ul></instructions><weight>1</weight></step><step name="digitalcert">
        <title>Digital certificate setup for SSL/TLS </title>
        <description>If your cloud provider uses SSL/TLS communication, you must obtain the necessary digital certificates and understand the type of  SSL/TLS authentication the cloud performs.</description>
		<step name="subStep1_1">	<title>Set up for server authentication</title>
<description>Set up for server authentication.</description>
			<step name="subStep1_1_1">
				<title>Add the cloud root CA certificate.</title>
<description>Add the cloud root CA certificate.</description>
<instructions>Issue the RACDCERT CERTAUTH ADD command: <p>RACDCERT CERTAUTH ADD(&lt;<i>dataset containing cloud root CA</i> >) WITHLABEL(’Cloud Root CA') TRUST</p></instructions>		
<weight>1</weight></step><step name="subStep_1_2_1"><title>Add the cloud intermediate CA certificate</title><description>Add the cloud intermediate CA certificate</description><instructions>(Optional) Use the RACDCERT CERTAUTH ADD command: <p>RACDCERT CERTAUTH ADD(&lt;<i>dataset containing cloud intermediate CA</i>>) WITHLABEL(’Cloud Intermediate CA') TRUST</p><p>Note: the intermediate CA certificate can be omitted if the cloud's key ring contains the intermediate CA certificate.</p><p>If the cloud identity certificate was signed by a root CA then the intermediate CA is also not necessary.</p></instructions><weight>1</weight></step><step name="SubStep1_3_1"><title>Virtual keyring</title><description>In this case we can use a virtual keyring in our SMS cloud construct.</description>
<instructions>For the SSL key in the SMS cloud construct, specify a virtual key ring by the name of *AUTH*/*</instructions>
<weight>1</weight></step>

		</step><step name="subStep2_1">	<title>Set up for mutual authentication</title>
<description>Set up for mutual authentication.</description>
			<step name="subStep2_1_1">
				<title>Add a key ring for DFSMS to use.</title>
<description>Add a key ring for DFSMS to use.</description>
<instructions>Issue the RACDCERT ID(DFHSM) command: <p>RACDCERT ID(DFHSM) ADDRING(<i>ring_name</i>)</p></instructions>
<weight>1</weight>							
</step><step name="subStep_2_3"><title>Add the z/OS host identity certificate with the private key and its CA certificate</title><description>Add the z/OS host identity certificate with the private key and its CA certificate</description>
<instructions>Specify the following commands:<p>RACDCERT CERTAUTH ADD(&lt;<i>dataset containing X</i>>) WITHLABEL(’zOS host Root CA') TRUST</p><p>RACDCERT ID(DFHSM) ADD(&lt;<i>dataset containing C and private key</i>>) WITHLABEL(’zOS host cert') TRUST PASSWORD('…')</p> 
</instructions><weight>1</weight>
</step>
<step name="subStep_2_3_1"><title>Add the cloud root CA certificate</title><description>Add the cloud root CA certificate.</description>
<instructions>Specify the following command: <p>RACDCERT CERTAUTH ADD(&lt;<i>dataset containing A</i>>) WITHLABEL('Cloud Root CA') TRUST</p></instructions>
<weight>1</weight></step></step>		
<step name="subStep_2_4_1"><title>Connect all the certificates to the key ring</title><description>Connect all the certificates to the key ring</description><instructions>Specify the following commands:<p>RACDCERT ID(DFHSM) CONNECT(CERTAUTH LABEL(’zOS host Root CA') ring(CLOUD))</p><p>RACDCERT ID(DFHSM) CONNECT(CERTAUTH LABEL(’Cloud Root CA') ring(CLOUD))</p><p>RACDCERT ID(DFHSM) CONNECT(LABEL(’zOS host cert') ring(CLOUD) DEFAULT)</p> </instructions><weight>1</weight>
</step>		
<step name="subStep_2_5_1"><title>Real key ring</title><description>In this case we can use a real key ring in our SMS cloud construct.</description>
<instructions>For the SSL key in the SMS cloud construct, specify a real key ring by the name of  DFHSM/ring_name</instructions>
<weight>1</weight></step></step><step name="SMSSetup"><title>SMS Setup</title><description>Set up SMS to support  transparent cloud tiering.</description><instructions>Perform the following SMS configuration steps to enable transparent cloud tiering:
<ul><li>(Optional) Allocate a backup SMS configuration data set (BACKUP.SCDS), a backup active configuration data set (BACKUP.ACDS), 
and a new active configuration data set (NEW.ACDS) that you will use for a new SMS configuration. </li>
<li>Make a backup of your existing SMS configuration, using the SETSMS SAVESCDS(scds.name) command.</li>
<li>Make a backup of your existing active SMS configuration data set, using the SETSMS SAVEACDS(acds.name) command.</li>
<li>Use new ISMF Cloud panels to define cloud construct(s) in the active SMS source configuration data set
 (required information: cloud name, provider, identity (credentials), endpoint, port, SSL version, SSL key).</li>
<li>Validate the new SMS configuration in the active source configuration data set, using ISMF.</li>
<li>Copy the active SCDS into the new ACDS, using the SETSMS COPYSCDS(new.scds) command.</li>
<li>Activate the new SMS active configuration data set, using the SETSMS ACDS(new.acds) command.</li>

</ul>.
</instructions><weight>1</weight></step>
<step name="SDMsetup"><title>SDM  Setup</title><description>Enable SDM for transparent cloud tiering.</description><instructions>Define SAF resources to control access to the OBJSTORE ILK on the ANTRQST API.  
It is recommended that the following FACILITY class profile is defined with a universal access of NONE:<ul><li>STGADMIN.ANT.ESS.OBJSTORE</li></ul></instructions><weight>1</weight></step>
<step name="DSSsetup"><title>DFSMSdss Setup</title><description>Enable DFSMSdss commands for transparent cloud tiering.</description><instructions>Define SAF resources to control access to the CLOUD keyword on the DFSMSdss DUMP and RESTORE commands, by granting READ access to the following FACILITY 
class profiles:<ul><li>STGADMIN.ADR.DUMP.CLOUD</li><li>STGADMIN.ADR.RESTORE.CLOUD</li></ul></instructions><weight>1</weight></step>
<step name="HSMsetup"><title>DFSMShsm Setup</title><description>Enable DFSMShsm commands for transparent cloud tiering.</description><instructions>Enable the CP Assist for Cryptographic Functions.<p>Define DFSMShsm to z/OS UNIX System Services as a superuser, and the RACF user ID must have a default RACF group which has an OMVS segment with a group id (GID). 
The user ID must also have an OMVS segment with the following parameters: UID(0) HOME('/').</p><p>Define SAF resources to control access to the CLOUD keyword on the HMIGRATE end user command, by granting READ access to the following FACILITY 
class profile:<ul><li>STGADMIN.ARC.ENDUSER.HMIGRATE.CLOUD</li></ul></p><p>Set the password that DFSMShsm uses when communicating with the Object Storage account:<ul><li>Issue the following operator command: SETSYS CLOUD(NAME(cloud_name) CCREDS)
</li><li>The system will prompt for the cloud password in a WTOR and the response will not be echoed back to the console. If the cloud password is case sensitive, 
use the System Command Extension from the SDSF log when replying to the WTOR. (The System Command Extension can be started by typing a forward slash (/) 
on the Command Input line in the SDSF system log.).</li>
<li>The cloud password must be secured. IBM recommends that the Security Administrator who is administering the Cloud Storage accounts be the one who enters this password.</li></ul></p></instructions><weight>1</weight></step>

<step name="enablemsg"><title>Enable status messages</title><description>Enable status messages </description><instructions>Specify ENABLE(AOM0496I) in DEVSUP<i>xx</i>, when exceptions need to be looked at. Note: the default is DISABLE(AOM0496I).</instructions><weight>1</weight></step>
<step name="users"><title>Inform users</title><description>Inform users about cloud commands</description><instructions>Inform users about the various commands for using transparent cloud tiering, including the new DFSMSdss and DFSMShsm commands.</instructions><weight>1</weight></step>

</workflow>
